Guide to the Noah Porter Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Noah Porter papers
1781-1889
MS 1131
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.25
Correspondence, notes, sermons, lectures, teaching materials, and memorabilia of Noah Porter. The major part of the correspondence, as well as of the other papers, deals with Porter's responsibilities as professor and president at Yale College. The few family letters are from his father, Rev. Noah Porter of Farmington, and from his wife, Mary Taylor Porter. His writings include lectures and sermons delivered at Yale College, 1871-1886. Also documenting his academic career are grade books, reports of Yale College committees, including one on the location of college buildings (1866), and papers relating to the American Education Society (1874-1889).
Porter, Noah, 1811-1892
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Noah Porter Papers were brought together in 1980 from the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscripts Library, the Yale Treasurer's Records, and the autograph collections and miscellaneous collections in Manuscripts and Archives.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Correspondence. II. Writings. III. Other Papers.
Scope and Contents
The Noah Porter Papers consist of correspondence, writings, and miscellaneous papers brought together in 1980 from the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, the Yale Treasurer's Records, and the autograph collections and miscellaneous collections in this department. There is much Porter material remaining in other collections, especially the Woolsey Family Papers.
Series I, CORRESPONDENCE, consists mainly of letters to and from Noah Porter, professor of moral philosophy and metaphysics and president of Yale College. About three-fourths were written while he was serving as president, and the rest were written earlier. There is hardly any continuity in this correspondence, but most letters deal with Porter's responsibilities as professor and president. Besides his correspondence, there are five letters by his father, the Rev. Noah Porter of Farmington, and a few letters to his father and his wife.
Series II, WRITINGS, consists of sermons, lectures, and notes of President Noah Porter, mainly originating during his presidency but including a few items from his student days at Yale. These are mainly manuscripts of published and unpublished works.
Series III, OTHER PAPERS, is a miscellaneous gathering of personal, professional, and presidential papers by Noah Porter and others.
Biographical / Historical
Noah Porter: Congregational clergyman, educator, president of Yale College; B.A., Yale, 1831; studied at the Yale Divinity School with Nathaniel W. Taylor; ordained in 1836; from 1843-1846 pastor of the Second Congregational Church in Springfield, Massachusetts; president of Yale from 1871-1886.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Sermons; Clergy; College presidents; Educators; Porter, Mary Taylor, 1813-1888; Porter, Noah, 1781-1866; Porter, Noah, 1811-1892; Yale University -- Buildings; Yale University -- History; Yale University -- Officals and employees; Yale Corporation; Yale University. Dept. of Philosophy
- Correspondence, Series I
  - Noah Porter, 1781-1866
    - Outgoing (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Incoming (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Noah Porter, 1811-1892 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Incoming
      - By topic (Box 1, Folder 2-8)
      - By writer (Box 1, Folder 9-43)
    - Outgoing (by recipient) (Box 1, Folder 44-53)
  - Mary (Taylor) Porter, 1813-1888: incoming (Box 1, Folder 54)
- NOTES AND WRITINGS, Series II
  - Baccalaureate addresses, 1876-1886 (Box 2, Folder 55-58)
  - Student papers, 1827, 1830 (Box 2, Folder 59-60)
  - Notes in German on philosophy lectures of Adolph Helfferich and logic lectures of Friedrich Adolf Trendelenburg, [1853?] (Box 2, Folder 60A)
  - Notes, sermons, and lectures
    - 1871-1877 (Box 2, Folder 61-63)
    - 1883-1886, undated (Box 3, Folder 64-72)
- OTHER PAPERS, Series III
  General note
  Oversize Material
  - Receipt, 1833 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Documents re: sabbatical in Germany, 1853 (Box 3, Folder 74-75)
  - Recommendation, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Engraving (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Grade and attendance books, 1861, 1866-1867 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Report on location of college buildings, 1866 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Critique of Human Intellect, 1869? (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Reports of term exam committees, 1871-1883 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Subscription book for Porter and other medallions, 1874 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Ms. letter asking for money for medical department, 1876 (Box 3, Folder 82A)
  - Papers of Porter and T. Dwight re the Am. Ed. Soc., 1874-1889 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Recommendation, 1875 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Documents re the John Haynes Fund, 1878, 1881 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Minute re: Porter's retirement, 1886 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Calling card (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Honorary degree, Passports, 1866-1886 (Box 4)
- INDEX OF CORRESPONDENTS
  - Angell, James Burrill (1829-1916). ALS to Noah Porter,, Univ. of Michigan., 1874 May 8
    General
    2 p. 21 1/2 cm.
  - Caulfield, Richard (1823-1881). ALS to Noah Porter,, Cork, Ireland., 1882 February 8
  - Eaton, Daniel Cady (1834-1895). A. Df. of a report to Noah Porter,, New Haven, Conn., 1877 June 4
    This report lists courses which Eaton proposed to offer and contrasts the equipment for botanical studies at Harvard and at Yale. With this is a statement also in his hand concerning the "Botany optional" at Yale, which may be Eaton's copy of Porter's note on the subject. 3 p. and 1 l.
  - Harrison, Francis Edwin (1830-1887). ALS to Noah Porter,, New Haven, Conn., 1873 May 26
  - Helfferich, Adolph (1813-1894).
    Geschichte der neueren Philosophie nach den Vorlesungen des Herrn Dr. A. Helfferich, probably written for, or used by, Noah Porter, president of Yale College, while in Germany in 1853-54.
    1 v. 22 cm.
  - McDermott, Charles (1808-1884). ALS to Noah Porter,, Monticello, Arkansas., 1873 August 6
    Concerning the Woolsey Fund.
  - Marsh, Othniel Charles (1831, Y 1860). Copy of ALS to President Noah Porter,, New Haven, Conn., 1873 June 4
    2 p. 18 1/2 cm. Portrait.
  - Neilson, Joseph (1813-1888). ALS to Noah Porter,, Brooklyn, N.Y., 1879 May 6
    The body of the letter is in a different hand from that of Mr. Neilson's subscription and signature.
    About Rufus Choate.
    3 p. 26 1/2 cm.
  - Trendelenburg, Friedrich Adolph (1802-1872).
    Outline of lectures on logic, in German by F. A. Trendelenburg, University of Berlin, probably made for or used by Noah Porter, president of Yale College, while in Germany in 1853-54.
    1 v. 20 1/2 cm.
  - Van Name, Addison (1835-1922). Memorandum stating that William Miller had deposited his bronze medallion of President N. Porter for presentation to the college,, New Haven, Conn., 1874 July 7
    With annotation of H. N. Day.
    Enclosed is a notebook, showing subscriptions for Mr. Miller's medallions of T. D. Woolsey, N. Porter, with proposals for those of W. M. Evart and Morrison Waite.
    1 p. 20 cm.
  - Wooding, W. M. of Newark, N.J. INTUITIONS; an article written after seeing a criticism of Noah Porter's Human Intellect in a March issue of The Catholic World.
    3 p. 32 cm.